SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Career Overview

8 years of experience in Software testing and Quality Assurance. Rich professional experience with clients across Retail, Consumer Goods, Telecoms while leading/supporting testing activities, test management and QA implementations from offshore and well as from onshore. Key Focus Areas: Big data Testing in Hadoop, enhancing data quality in a continuous delivery model by strategizing and performing data validation facilitating client data analytics and business report generation Key Capabilities: Software Development Lifecycle including Scaled Agile Framework and Waterfall model, Test Strategy and Test Management, Test Execution, Project Management, Establish effective onshore-offshore delivery model, Process Implementation.

Qualifications

- Software Testing Requirement Analysis, Test Planning, Test Execution, Component-Integration-Regression Testing Defect Management UI Validation, Web Services Testing, Back End Data Validation, Mobile Application Testing
- Relational and Un-Structured Database System Scaled Agile Framework
- Tools: Mercury Quality Center, HPALM, JIRA, Test Rail(JIRA), Fiddler, Advanced Rest Client, Selenium
- Databases: Hive, SQL Server
- Web: HTML, CSS, XML SOAP, RESTFUL
- Frameworks: Hadoop
- Operating Systems: Windows, Unix
- SDLC : Agile, Waterfall

Work Experience

Senior Software Engineer 01/2007 to 12/2015 Surveymonkey

- Professional Projects Summary Pricing Knowledge Platform: 2012 Till Date Client: Wal-Mart This project aims at analyzing various
 aspects of Walmart's pricing policies and comparing Walmart's price with that of the competitors and generating various reports which
 would help the business to take critical and competitive pricing decision.
- Overall Roles and Responsibilities: Performed the key role of the QA lead in the client location; worked closely with the client team to understand the business requirements and built effective test strategy to ensure high quality work products being delivered.
- Worked in close co-ordination with the development team, other members of the scrum team and the business stake holders to ensure
 quality deliverables are achieved by driving efficient defect management.
- Created UAT test cases and worked in close proximity with the business team during UAT phase and helped in taking critical production go-no go decision.
- Established an efficient onshore-offshore delivery model Performed project management activities, performed sprint wise work estimation by load and velocity calculation, tracked work progress using various metrics like burn down chart etc., validated resource utilization using Microsoft Project tool, prepared DSR[daily status report] and various internal metrics to report project health Testing Responsibilities: Validation of output of Oozie workflow against the output of the statistical data model by running oozie workflow and analyzing the outputs.
- Source to Target Data Validation, Metadata testing, Data Completeness Testing, Data Accuracy and Data Quality Testing, Incremental
 testing for Data Integrity Data validation from Flat table to the Reporting Tool; Validation of the Report generated Testing of web services
 established between the front end and the back end GUI Testing to validate GUI aspects of the front end reports.
- Technical Tools: Hadoop, Hive, Green plum, Putty, Hue, Advanced Rest Client, Tableau Achievements: Project started in PoC (Proof of Concept) stage; Ensured the delivery of reliable and efficient modules which established a fully functional project with stable applications and reporting mechanisms in place.
- Successful completion of PoC project ensuring delivery of high quality product won client's trust and the team size has grown from initial 3
 members to a 16 members QA team.
- promoted to QA Team Lead for performance and client value creation in the project.
- Awarded with 'Star of the Month' title by my organization for Business Value creation with the client.

01/2010 to 01/2011 Bickford Senior Living

- BT Global Services helps multi-site organizations to master the complexity of business communication.
- The objective of this testing project is to capture entire journey of order entry, quotation, service provision, delivery and maintenance to satisfy respective Change Requests.
- Overall Roles and Responsibilities: Role: Test Designer Analyzed business requirement by working closely with the client team and create
 effective high level and low level test scenarios Responsible for helping the test execution team in understanding the test requirements &
 providing solution to issues faced during execution.
- Responsible for analyzing and testing newly launched applications.
- Providing the estimation for releases through Estimated Test Points (ETP).
- Task Assignment and Allocation of Work schedule to Team Members.
- Achievements: Played the role of the key member to receive transition from the incumbent team for the Business As Usual module
 Effectively completed transition and presented successful Reverse KT towards the client team and played a key role in getting the project
 awarded to my organization by the client team.
- Taken up instrumental role in forming an offshore testing team and equipped them with required knowledge to carry out test execution responsibilities ensuring quality deliverables.
- Team started functioning immediately meeting the demand of Agile delivery ensuring seamless transition.
- · Awarded with 'Shining Star' award for playing key role in the successful transition and building efficient team.

- MCCP (Multi Channel Contact Platform) is a project to create an extended platform/technical foundation and resource capabilities to support multiple brands conducting eCommerce in the United Kingdom
- The goal is a seamless integration of all selling channels and customer contact points including eCommerce to allow easier integration and synchronization between various channels and improve overall customer experience regardless of channels.
- Overall Roles and Responsibilities: Role: Test Engineer Requirement analysis, test case preparation, test data preparation, test execution, defect management and status reporting Main resting responsibilities performed: component testing, usability testing, integration testing, interface validation and regression testing Usability Testing: Translated the design of the pages from the VISIO Wireframe to HTML pages, Developed Mockups of the Application pages using HTML & CSS, suggested design changesto improve the look & feel of the pages from user experience perspective Test Data Management: Helped in managing all test data required for the project, gathered 3rd party data, analysed and created test data with diverse attributes needed for Integration Product Testing(IPT) and UAT, tracked data burn and performed data refresh.
- Performed Best Buy UK mobile application testing.
- Achievements: During production go live of the application, performed the key role of Integration Tester in the client side and involved in
 data validation across interfaces, assisted with diagnosis of third party integration issues, reviewed technical payloads against API
 specifications, did trouble shooting of common errors and assisted in issue diagnosis and fixing.
- Also helped business by identifying key areas of testing during UAT phase, helped in creating UAT test suite and played instrumental role in successful go live of the application.

Education and Training

Bachelor of Engineering Jadavpur University City, State, India

Year of Passing: 2007 Resume

Skills

go live, Agile, aims, API, business communication, competitive, Concept, CSS, Client, Data Management, Data Validation, Databases, Database, delivery, diagnosis, driving, eCommerce, Engineer, XML, functional, GUI, HTML, Team Lead, managing, Microsoft Project, Windows, Operating Systems, order entry, policies, Pricing, Product Testing, progress, project management, Quality, QA, reporting, Requirement, selling, scrum, SDLC, SOAP, Software Testing, SQL Server, strategy, Structured, Tableau, trouble shooting, Unix, Usability Testing, Validation, VISIO, wise, workflow